Odencrantz, Louise C. (Louise Christine), 1884-1969. Papers, 1909-1968: A Finding Aid
Papers, 1909-1968
MC 195
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Louise C. Odencrantz, 1884-1969
1/2 file box
Correspondence, manuscripts, programs, of Louise C. (Louise Christine) Odencrantz, an investigator in industrial relations.
Accession number: 1367
The papers of Louise C. Odencrantz were deposited with the Schlesinger Library in May 1968 by Louise C. Odencrantz.
BIOGRAPHY
Louise C. Odencrantz was born on August 22, 1884, in Gothenburg, Nebraska; she received her B.A. from Barnard College in 1907 and her M.A. in Social Sciences from Columbia University in 1908. From 1908 to 1915 she was an investigator in industrial relations for the Russell Sage Foundation. From 1915 through 1919 she supervised both the New York State and the United States Employment Bureaus on the wartime employment of women in industry. As Personnel Director (1919-1924) for Smith Kaufmann, Inc., a New York City silk ribbon company, she was active in labor negotiations and employee welfare programs. In 1922 she helped organize the International Industrial Relations Association and attended its congressesas United States delegate in 1922, 1925, and 1928. From 1927 to 1936 she was Director of the Employment Center for the Handicapped in New York. For the next three years she helped organize and train new staff for the New York State Division of Placement and Unemployment Insurance, and during World War II was Executive Director of the Social Work Vocational Bureau in New York City. She retired from the business world in 1946, remaining active in many volunteer programs until her death in April 1969.
LCO was the author of Italian Women in Industry (1915) and The Social Worker in Family, Medical and Psychiatric Social Work (1927), and co-author of Industrial Conditions in Springfield, Ill. (1915) and Public Employment Services in the United States (1938).
CONTAINER LIST
Box 1: 1-14
INVENTORY
- Biographical information: 2 page typescript resume by LCO, July 11, 1968; and 3 articles re LCO., 1.
- Photographs:, 2.
  - Portrait, signed, circa 1947.
  - Newsclippings: May 21, 1922, LCO as a member of the Manhattanville Health Society; February 1953, LCO with "New York School Alumni" at the International Conference of Social Work in Madras, India.
- Correspondence:, 3.
  - John H. Finley (President, Univ. of New York), TLS, June 16, 1919, concerning LCO's speech at Educational Congress.
    For text of speech, see folder 4.
  - Frances Perkins (Industrial Commissioner, New York State, Department of Labor), TLS, June 10, 1929.
- Speeches (typescript):, 4.
  - "Methods and Results of Training Women For Industry," given May 19, 1919, at Educational Congress, Albany.
  - "Personnel Work in America," given July 4, 1922, at the International Welfare Conference, La Haye Malherbe, France.
  - "The Place of Personnel Work in a Business Organization," given October 9, 1922 before the New Haven Industrial Relations Council.
- Published speeches:, 5.
  - "Personnel Work in America," Personnel Administration, August 1922, pp. 5-15.
    Typescript in folder 4.
  - "Personnel Work in America," Welfare Work, September 1922, pp. 166-168.
  - "Personnel Work in Factories," Public Health Nurse, August 1923; two copies, one with marginalia, pp. 395-400.
  - "The Employment Problem of the Physically Handicapped," Hospital Social Service, 1930, pp. 463-470.
  - "Medical Social Work in Industrial Medicine and Traumatic Surgery," Hospital Social Service, 1932, pp. 249-255.
  - "Occupational Therapy and the Placement of the Handicapped in Industry," Occupational Therapy and Rehabilitation, June 1935, pp. 189-195.
  - "Recent Developments in Employment Services," Occupations, the Vocational Guidence Magazine, January 1940; adaptation of a paper presented at Metropolitan Conference, New York, pp. 3-5 (2 copies.)
- Articles (typescript):, 6.
  - "Personnel Management and the Silk Industry," November 1921. 9 pages with some corrections.
    Published version in folder 7.
  - Report, July 1-September 30, 1934: New York State Employment Service - Division for the Handicapped, October 15, 1934.
  - "Unemployable," March 5, 1935. Brief article on handicapped workers.
- Published articles:, 7.
  See also folder 9.
  - "The Irregularity of Employment of Women Factory Workers," The Survey, May 1, 1909, pp. 196-210.
  - "Employment of Women and Children in Selected Industries," The Survey, January 2, 1914, pp. 498-499.
  - "State's First Employment Bureau a Success," New York Times Magazine, March 2, 1916, p. 9.
  - "Common Sense in Industry: How Silk Ribbons are Manufactured Without Strikes or Lockouts," The Metropolis, June 1, 1921, p. 10.
  - "Employment Management and the Silk Industry," American Silk Journal, December 1921, pp. 57-60.
    For typescript, see folder 6.
  - "Vocations for the Handicapped," Occupations, the Vocational Guidence Magazine, October 1933, by LCO and Seville Millar.
  - How Physically Handicapped People Find Work: A Manual of Placement Procedures, prepared by Division of the Handicapped, LCO Director, September 1935. 30 pages.
  - "These Jobs Beg For Workers," The Survey, September 1945, pp. 219-220. (2 copies.)
- International Industrial Relations Association (I.R.I.): programs, reports, and other official documents., 8.
  - 1922 Congress: Program, with annotations; and Report of Interim Committee.
  - 1925 Congress: Introduction to Report of the Proceedings.
  - Report of Open Meeting..., July 10-15, 1926: The Development of Scientific Methods in Industry, and their Effect on Those Taking Part.
  - 1928 Congress: Preliminary Program; and Program with LCO's annotations.
  - Typescript notes of an informal I.R.I. meeting, Westport, Conn., October 27, 1928.
  - Call for the Congress of the I.R.I. to meet in Amsterdam, Holland, August 23-29, 1931.
  - Statutes of the International Association for the Study and Improvement of Human Relations and Conditions in Industry, 12 pages.
  - Application for membership in the I.R.I.
  - Miscellaneous: Invitation, bulletin, etc., in French and Italian.
- Articles about I.R.I. Congresses by LCO:, 9.
  - "Industrial Welfare Work," The Survey, August 15, 1922, pp. 631-632.
  - "International Industrial Welfare Conference," Personnel Administration, October 1922, pp. 3-6 (2 copies.)
  - "International Industrial Welfare Congress, Flushing, Holland, June 19-26, 1925," Bulletin of the Taylor Society, October 1925, pp. 231-232.
  - "The International Industrial Welfare and Personnel Congress, Holland, June 19-26, 1925," American Management Review, November 1925, pp. 341-343.
  - "Congress of the International Industrial Relations Association," The Compass, July-August 1928, pp. 3-4.
  - "Cambridge Congress of the I.R.I....," The Personnel Journal, October 1928, pp. 226-235 (2 copies.)
- Book Reviews by LCO, 1926-1934., 10.
- Books by LCO: Leaflets, reviews:, 11.
  - Industrial Conditions in Springfield, Ill., by LCO and Zenas L. Potter. Review, 1916.
  - The Social Worker in Family, Medical and Psychiatric Social Work, leaflets, reviews, 1928-1929.
- Smith and Kaufmann, Inc. Labor contracts, agreements, advertising, etc., 1920-1923., 12.
- Articles and newclippings about LCO's work, 1922-1930., 13.
- Miscellaneous articles and newclippings, 1922-1968., 14.
Additional catalog entries
International Industrial Relations Association; Perkins, Frances, 1880-1965; Handicapped--Employment; Personnel Management; Women in Industry